software engineering radio episode 68
garbage collection and transactional
memory with Dan Grossman
hello listeners welcome to another
episode of software engineering radio in
this episode we are going to talk to Dan
Grossman about transactional memory and
garbage collection about an analogy
between the two topics so Dan welcome
thank you so then before we actually dig
into the topic why don't you introduce
yourself to our listeners sure I'm Dan
Grossman I'm a faculty member at the
University of Washington in Seattle and
I joined the faculty here about four
years ago after finishing my PhD at
Cornell University before that I was a
university student at Rice University in
Texas and my background has always been
in programming languages particularly
safe languages languages for increasing
robustness and software quality I used
to work more on low-level languages see
like languages or do you want to
implement an operating system or
low-level sort of systems code and more
recently I've become very interested in
concurrency and trying to make
programming easier for multi-core
architectures and sort of the mass
parallel programming that we're told is
on the horizon mm-hmm okay and and in
this year's oops law you have got a
paper about transactional memory and
garbage collection so most people I
think know what garbage collection is
but can you give us a brief introduction
about what transactional memory is all
about and what it's used for sure
transactional memory is the idea that
your memory operations you know a memory
is just things you you know you can read
from locations and write to locations
and typically if you're down in assembly
language or even up in the language like
Java you do individual reads and writes
and as soon as you do them anything
that's happening concurrently another
thread or whatever could see those
there's only sort of one memory and it
works at the granularity of individual
reads and writes with transactional
memory you just have the ability to
group a collection of reads and writes
into
transaction very much like you can group
a bunch of database operations into a
transaction in the database setting with
persistent storage but now we're really
dealing with program state with with
volatile memory and you can group them
together and by grouping them together
you guarantee that either all of them
happen or none of them happen and that
any concurrent observer sees all of the
updates at the same time mm-hmm so
actually just to connect this to a
previous episode on su radio we talked
with Brian gets and David Holmes about
concurrency about advanced concurrency
and right at the end they mentioned
transactional memory is something that's
on the horizon that might revolutionize
concurrent programming so can you
provide us an example of how we would
use transactional memory if it were
available and of course it's always a
bit of a problem to to talk about source
code in an audio-only form but but let's
try how will I ever do this without
waving my head well no it's so the
simplest way to think about it from a
programming perspective is that it gives
you a synchronization mechanism that you
didn't have before
right now if you program in Java the
most common synchronization mechanism is
locking using synchronized statements
okay and the reason why you use a
synchronized statement is because you
want the things in that statement to all
occur you know while no other thread has
that lock yep and here we're getting an
even stronger guarantee we're saying
let's get locks completely out of the
picture and you say the same thing you
say atomic left curly brace and then
some statement and then right curly
brace so instead of saying synchronize
and a lock to acquire you just say
atomic it's just a key word and you
don't specify any lock at all and that
just says that the computation that
happens in this block has to appear to
happen all at once to any other thread
mm-hm
and and again to connect to the other
episode in some sense it's basically
moving something that has been provided
in the form of libraries and which had
to be obeyed as a protocol
bring that into a language and making it
more declarative and by doing that of
course the compiler and the runtime
system has more options to optimize
right that's exactly right in the sense
that when you have an atomic block
you're not specifying any sort of
particularly anything like that you're
just saying this has to happen all at
once now absolutely the role of the
compiler in the runtime system now is to
preserve the illusion of it happening
all at once
yeah and what it really tries to do is
preserve as much parallelism as a can um
and the way it basically does that
there's you know there's people who very
very smart researchers who've devoted
years to the details but the basic idea
is that you have these different atomic
blocks or transactions running at the
same time and you just do enough
bookkeeping to make sure that they're
accessing disjoint memory mm-hm
yeah and as long as they're accessing
destroy memory it's fine to let them
happen at the same time the programmer
can't tell that they happen at the same
time yeah okay so your your claim in the
paper is that transactional memory is to
shared memory concurrency as garbage
collection is to memory management so so
before we look at the analogy and
actually when I read the paper I was
quite intrigued this is a really cool
stuff I mean it's really interesting how
you wrote the paper and and so let's
first recap we introduced a little bit
about garbage collection artworks and
and and things like the basic idea of
different algorithms so we can connect
to that when we talk about transactional
memory later I think that's a great idea
and maybe something else I could say
even before that is that this is a an
essay which is a slightly different kind
of paper yeah oops oh so there aren't
you know nothing we'll talk about or
nothing in the paper is necessarily a
new technical result sure it's really a
new perspective this analogy is not
something that's been focused on before
or even said before so this is a really
a reorganization of existing knowledge
yep so to do that you really have to
start from the beginning and you have to
give a perspective on you know what is
garbage collection and you know
I don't you know you can sort of take
the view of oh well it's that feature
that means you never have to write
freeze and you don't have any space
leaks and you don't have any dangling
pointer dereferences but if you take a
step back that's all true but really
what garbage collection is is a language
mechanism by which the runtime system
can reuse space in a way that the
programmer can never tell hmm you know
from a language definition perspective
in a language like Java all you do is
allocate new objects and they live
forever and it's up to the garbage
collector to maintain that illusion
while actually reusing memory and the
key approximation that it uses and I
think it's important to realize it's an
approximation is this idea of reach
ability okay the way garbage collectors
work from 35,000 feet is it looks at all
the variables you're still using any
program everything on your call stack
and all your global variables your
static fields and it sees what objects
those point to and then what objects the
fields of those objects point to and so
on transitively and it keeps all of that
and it collects everything else which it
calls the garbage and the reason why I
call it an approximation is this can
lead to keeping objects around longer
than necessary right and so you know for
example if you put a very large data
structure in a global variable and never
use the global variable again you're
just wasting space there's nothing that
garbage collectors can do about it so
and and based on that on that basic idea
and and and and concept of readability
there are probably a couple of different
higher level algorithms and probably a
couple of tricks that you can use to
optimize these kinds of things right
right at 35,000 feet you know I just
said it finds everything that's
reachable if you go down one level
deeper you say well well how does it do
that and you know one approach which is
called tracing garbage collection and
that's an approach that subsumes you
know some phrases there are some ideas
that listeners might have heard like
copying garbage collection or mark-sweep
is
to have the garbage collector literally
literally go through memory you know
marking everything that it finds that
it's alive and another approach is to
basically use automated reference
counting so an automated reference
counting as the program is running the
system just keeps track of how many
references there are to each object and
when you reach zero you can go ahead and
collect the object because you know that
it's no longer reachable yep
there is also real-time garbage
collection is probably a very special
case for for well embedded systems right
that's right so this this phase if you
will of finding what's reachable is
something that's not under programmer
control and a language like Java it
could happen at any moment and if it
takes a long time that could mess up any
sort of application that has timing
needs you know that either soft timing
needs like you need an interactive
application or hard timing needs like
you need to respond to sensors and
signals like embedded systems have and
so taking a basic garbage collector and
and giving it the property that it never
stops the regular program for more than
a very small amount of time is something
that's been studied we have algorithms
to do it but it's significantly more
difficult than a basic garbage collector
mm-hmm okay so now that we talked about
GC garbage collection as an introduction
let's now look at an introduction to
concurrency and transactional memory
sure so what I did in this analogy is
really assumed from the beginning shared
memory concurrency so people who are
more familiar with message passing or
coordination languages there's a lot of
models of parallel programming Erling is
becoming quite hype these days with its
echo base to a message passing thing
absolutely and I'm actually a pretty big
fan of things like message passing
languages um but you know that's a topic
for another yes so you know for today
I'm really imagining really the parallel
is a model we have and in modern
object-oriented languages like Java
which is you have multiple threads a
thread can create a new thread these are
separate bits of control you might have
multiple running at the same time or you
might be time slicing one running one
for a little while and running another
and the way they communicate because
it's it's you know multi-threaded
programming is not interesting until the
threads communicate yeah it's one thread
write some data to a location and
another thread reads that location and
that's exactly what I mean by shared
memory and then the next step is well
how do they coordinate write how do how
does one thread know that the value has
been written how does another thread how
do you keep two threads from writing to
the same location at the same time and
to me in general that's what you have
synchronization mechanisms for and it's
it's all the things one learns about
typically in an undergraduate operating
systems course blocks monitors
semaphores all of those things that well
and you need something like that and
it's a classic result of parallel
computing that's given one you can
typically code up all the others but you
need something to the way I like to
think of it is restrict are the
interleavings of different threats right
you need to make sure that if one thread
is stopped at a particular point right
between two statements and that can
happen that another thread won't proceed
to read the partial results of some
computation that isn't finished yet
mm-hm and of course then then we have
all these problems resulting from that
about dead logs and life logs if you try
something forever or if you don't if you
don't well if you try to acquire a log
that's already acquired nobody never
released and stuff so that's the typical
problems you get from implementing
concurrency as a protocol without
language support that's a great point is
and we should definitely walk through
those problems is you have things like
deadlock which is a collection of
threads unable to make progress because
they're all waiting for something else
to do something before they continue yes
and in some sense what you've done there
is you've taken away too many possible
thread interleavings the programmer has
through a programmer area but if you get
rid of too many locks then you have some
interleavings you didn't want and those
are typically what we call race
conditions and this is exactly the
tightrope that programmers have to walk
when they're when they're Pro
coming with locks is uh if you if you do
too little locking you'll have race
conditions and if you do too much you'll
have that lock yeah yeah and okay so we
talked about before how a transactional
memory simplifies these things by making
things more declarative and giving the
runtime system well let's say the right
level of freedom to optimize what's
optimizable so is transactional memory a
software only thing or is it actually a
software hardware combination yes and
all the more so transactional memory has
been very very active as a research
topic in the last two or three years
both from the computer architecture
community and the parallel programming
parallel algorithms community and also
the programming languages community and
we having joint workshops and we're all
talking together and there's just been a
lot of work and to answer your question
more directly there's been several
different proposals on how to provide
transactional memory completely and
hardware mm-hm
so you can really imagine down at the
assembly language having new
instructions like begin transaction end
transaction and abort transaction yeah
so the idea is that after you say begin
any loads and stores you do you'll be
allowed to say abort and then it says if
none of them happen or you can say end
transaction or sometimes called commit
transaction and then they all become
available to other threads what's
particularly good in hardware is that
they can do conflict detection they can
do this runtime optimization of letting
things happen in parallel if they can
very effectively using ideas similar to
cache coherence protocols which we've
known how to do for many years what they
can't do as well and I don't mean to
criticize because there's been very good
research papers on how to do it these
long transactions transactions that
access more than just a few memory
locations and their software
implementations things done entirely
with existing instruction sets but just
through compiler techniques tend to do a
little bit better they also tend to be
slower you know typically when you can
do something in hardware so you do but
software is also more flexible we
and explore different algorithms and
incorporate new advancements much more
quickly and there's been important work
on hybrid systems so and I think that
many people believe that that's where
the production quality systems will end
up is that you will use hardware to try
to complete a transaction do you give a
best effort but the hardware will have
the ability to say I wasn't able to do
it and the system will fail over to a
software implementation and the
challenge in that research and this is
not research that I did is to have a
running system where there are software
transactions and hardware transactions
happening at the same time but of course
from a developer's perspective in some
way you don't care because as long as
the language provides the features I
don't care whether the compiler
delegates to the hardware or just does
it himself
you're absolutely right and what you do
care about is the semantics so you know
when I say the atomic happens all at
once what do I mean by that and there
are some caveats that we haven't talked
about yet and these are caveats that the
community is still working its way
through for example the vast majority of
systems do not let you do i/o while
you're in transaction because how are
you going to undo it so and there are
some other things that if you assumed
all the implementations are hardware or
you assumed all the implementations were
software you might have slightly
different lists of caveats and what we
and the transactions community need to
do and are working at is figuring out
what those differences are and and what
we should be promising and our
programming languages that on the one
hand let's program is not care and on
the other hand allows a range of
implementations hardware if you have it
software if you don't and so on so from
from your last couple of paragraphs
basically I derived that this is still a
research topic it's not not something
that's used in production right but I
guess it's implemented in probably there
is a JVM that's transactional memory
somewhere that's right so let's see it
is still an active research topic I
don't know of
mercial say jvm that you can use right
now with transactional memory there are
certainly publicly available research
prototypes on the other hand all the
major companies that write vm's write
big software systems produce a big big
chip numbers of multi-core chips are not
only aware of the transactional memory
research but have research and
development teams working on it you know
just to you know there's been published
papers on transactional memory from
research groups at in let's say in
alphabetical order Intel Microsoft and
Sun yeah so there's a lot of industrial
interest and I have no inside
information and I have no crystal ball
but I would say we're talking a small
number of years before some of these
ideas are available so is there any
relationship to optimistic concurrency
and lock-free concurrent algorithms
that's something else we talked about in
the episode with Brian and David quite
at the end in the area of advanced stuff
yes there's very much a connection and
here's how I like to explain it and I
hope the people who understand this
connection better than me will like my
explanation is that transactional memory
is an optimistic concurrent data
structure so just like you might have a
cue that works with optimistic and
concurrency and has operations like NQ
and DQ and things like that
transactional memory is just one that
has operations like begin transaction
end transaction
abort transaction read memory and write
memory and once you have that what's
great is that the programmers can just
or the compiler or whatever can just use
those operations and all the optimistic
concurrency is is under the hood it's
just in the implementation of the data
structure the same way that using an
optimist that Q should not be any more
difficult than using a traditional
pessimistic or lock basic you and I have
another analogy here that I really like
and hopefully you need
like to which is that think about error
correction if all of our application
programs had to deal with error
correcting codes for memory it would be
a huge burden yep we get it for free
because our memory does error correction
for us yeah and so the idea of
transactional memory is that we can get
the optimistic concurrency sort of once
and for all and as long as we use the
transactional memory system we get the
optimism without actually having to
understand the the clever algorithms
that are that are that are used inside
it ok
so let's get to the meat of the matter I
guess and talk about the analogy between
garbage collection transactional memory
so um maybe I should briefly explain how
you wrote the paper to end and then
explain the challenge of doing that on
the podcast so so what then actually did
was he wrote a bunch of paragraphs on
different aspects of garbage collection
and then basically took the wording of
these paragraphs literally and exchanged
a couple of nouns the idea was to have
basically take exactly the same text and
just explain exchanged a couple of nouns
and verbs and and take exactly the same
structure to explain transactional
memory and concurrency and you advised
that people should read this stuff twice
once to understand and then the second
time to to see the to see that the well
the correspondence between the two and
of course we can't do that in the
podcast so we have to retract the
analogy might not show as nicely as in
the paper when we discussed these things
now well I'm certainly comfortable with
the conversation throwing out some of
the interesting ideas and and then and
then of course you're right it is the
sort of thing that is best done from
reading it although this idea of an
analogy just like you explained it is
for an analogy to make sense I have to
convince you that I'm saying true things
about both occurring things about
garbage collection you agree this and
I'm saying things about transactional
memory that you agree with and then I
have a third obligation you know through
things on one side through things on the
other side which is that those things
things are so similar in structure that
something deep is going on yeah so and
so what we'll do now is we'll step
through these different aspects you've
been looking at and we'll put of course
the link to the paper into the show
notes so the people who want to look at
your actual at the document to see how
does it really plays out very nicely can
actually read this stuff of course so
let's look at the two problems and how
they are similar sure
so we've already I think talked about on
the transactional memory side but we'll
do both so the problem with doing memory
management and you have to think back to
programming in C or C++ without a
garbage collector and think about when
you were really thinking about memory
management is that you're trying to use
as little memory as possible because you
don't want to run out of space or use so
much space that your program is sluggish
or consumes a lot of resources yeah but
if you use too little your program will
actually be wrong right so on the one
hand you have space leaks or space
exhaustion you're keeping around too
much memory and you have a performance
problem on the other hand you have
dangling pointer dereferences if you d
allocate memory before you're actually
done with it then your program is
completely wrong mm-hmm so you have to
balance this correctness keeping memory
around as long as you need it and
performance not keeping it around any
longer so that's the memory management
side and let's see if I can switch to
the transit to the concurrency side yeah
this is something we talked about before
but it's worth repeating right next to
it they're gonna do the analogy which is
you're trying to have as much
parallelism as possible let multiple
threads run at the same time and if you
don't have enough of that you're not
actually writing a parallel program you
end up having the performance problem of
really only one thread running at a time
or if you're even worse than that
deadlocking and not having any threads
running at all so you want to try to
keep as much parallelism as possible
from a performance angle but if you have
too much do you end up with race
conditions multiple threads stomping on
the same memory at the same time and
then your program is typically not
correct
you end up reading two parts of a value
that don't make sense together and
things like that so we have the same
dilemma of if we do too much in this on
the performance side we'll give up
correctness and if we work too hard for
correctness we'll end up giving away the
very performance advantages we're trying
to achieve by going for parallelism
mm-hmm
and I think even in the way you talked
about it now that the analogy shines
through really cool let's go to the to
the next aspect which is the solution in
one case garbage collection in the other
case a transactional memory when you go
to solve either of these problems
manually you end up using pretty subtle
protocols protocols that all of the code
in your application has to obey so in
the memory management side maybe if
you're doing it manually you have an
extra field in each object with a
reference count or whether it's still
needed or you tightly control what can
point to what else so that you know when
you're done with something and when you
implement a garbage collector if you
ever have it turns out you do all the
same things you have subtle protocols
all of the memory in your system is laid
out in a certain way they'll be header
field there be a certain bits that are
set to one if you're done with something
and zero if you're not so all of these
subtle whole program protocols are there
but they're not a part of the program
they're now part of the runtime system
where people who devote their lives to
writing good garbage collectors and a
real domain-specific experts in that can
get it right exactly once now they don't
know anything about your application
which is the challenge you know any time
you try to have a one-size-fits-all
solution it's not going to be specially
tuned to the application but they know
how to write garbage collectors and so
then for transactional memory it's the
same idea that now what we want to do is
we want to somehow keep track of are
these two transactions accessing the
same memory and the other thing
transactions have to do is they have to
have some way to take multiple updates
to memory and export them all at the
same time
and the protocols in doing that are
extremely subtle and involve all of the
code in the application doing the same
thing and doing it correctly but again
we have experts people who have
developed these algorithms and can
implement them once and for all and get
them right mm-hmm okay and also both
cases aren't useful in every in every
scenario they are incomplete solutions
in some sense right yeah and you know I
think garbage collection is great and I
don't want to come across as saying
anything otherwise in the same for
transactional memory but certainly once
you understand the approximations that
these systems make you can understand
that I can certainly write programs
where they do very very poorly so in
garbage collection
remember this key approximation is
reachable whatever is still reachable
will stay live and any time that's a bad
match for what should stay live anytime
you have an application or a bunch of
live things reachable things are no
longer needed programmers should really
get involved and somehow make those
things not reachable either by using
special language features like weak
pointers except or simply going in and
adjusting their data structure is quite
manually to make things no longer
reachable and when you start going down
that path you realize that you're
reintroducing the problems of manual
memory manager to make things not
reachable not too soon those are
incorrect and not too late or the data
will stay around yeah and I have a
little example in the paper in fact it
says if you are a very very stubborn
Java programmer who really wanted to do
manual memory management you can do it
you can set up a raise of objects and
when you're done with an object put it
back in the array and things like that
and and you really regain all of the
difficulties of manual memory management
and that's something that you might
actually want to do in an embedded
real-time systems where it's important
that the amount of memory is is well
it's constant and is also known in
advance when the system is built
deployed that's absolutely right and
I've even seen situations and people who
write garbage collectors don't like when
programmers do this but I've certainly
seen programs where for certain very
performance critical classes and and
algorithms people will do things like
have an array of packet objects so
simply cycle through it reusing the same
packet object memory rather than
constantly creating new packet objects
and freeing them and and going around
the loop and it really depends on your
system and your garbage collector people
often have the intuition and that
improves performance it really depends
on the system they're they're often not
correct yeah but it depends okay
TM site so on the transactional memory
side we have an approximation that is
the analogy of this reachability
approximation and that is that we don't
let two transactions proceed in parallel
if they have a memory conflict and that
almost means access the same memory it
turns out that as long as they're both
just reading the same memory we
typically allow parallel happen in that
case
but if there's a read write or write
write conflict we will not allow them to
both proceed and there are situations
where that is unnecessarily conservative
for example if they are both just
incrementing some counter it's just used
to say generate unique identifiers it
doesn't really matter that they can
flicked
one of them writes to to the counter the
next one writes three the next one
writes four doesn't really matter but
from the system's perspective from the
implementer of the transactional memory
it doesn't know that it sees that
because of this conflict
one thread saw the value three when it
should have gotten the value two and in
some sense only the application can know
that it doesn't matter whether it saw -
or three it just has to be a unique
value hmm and then I go ahead and show
that the extreme case just like a Java
programmer can regain the pluses and
minuses of manual memory management
someone program with transactional
memory
can write a locker class can go ahead
and implement locks on top of
transactional memory and then choose the
program in terms of method calls like
acquire lock and release lock yeah and
and then they'll have the same race
conditions and deadlock potentials in
their application that they had before
mmm very nice so I think these these
three aspects the problem solutions and
the incompleteness of the solution is
probably well from my perspective it's
the core of the analogy but it goes even
it goes even further I guess and you're
absolutely right that that is the core
of the analogy but then some of the
details turn out to push the idea
further so in in garbage collection it
turns out the two very basic approaches
are tracing which subsumes copying and
mark sweep and reference counting and
and and it turns out in for a few years
ago there was a very nice paper relating
these two basic approaches and showing
that they're actually duals kind of
complete opposites of each other in some
sense tracing traces be live data and
reference counting traces the dead data
and that's a much harder thing to to see
and I'll have to point you to that work
I think it was 2005 annual conference so
we will find out I'm sorry 2004 a paper
a unified theory of garbage collection
on the transactional memory side now we
have to get into just at the very
highest level how transactional memory
is implemented and again there's two
basic approaches one is that a
transaction while it's running goes
ahead and updates memory but then if it
can't complete because there's some
conflict with another transaction it
undoes or rolls back everything that it
had done previously the other
possibility is to not update shared
memory but instead while a transaction
is running it works on a private copy
and then if it successfully completes
then it reflects all the changes back to
shared memory using a complicated
protocol to do that and the interesting
thing how these two are opposites is
that if you do the update in place the
first version I talked about then
the transaction is trivial and aborting
in it is rather difficult yes and if you
do it with the private memory its exact
opposite aborting it is trivial and
committing it is quite difficult
hmm and and difficult also in sense of
performance cost that's right in both
cases the cost is usually of the
difficult part is proportional to the
number of memory locations that you
wrote to them which is good news and bad
news that doesn't sound big but remember
of course you already took the time in
your application to write to them yeah
so it's at least a proportional comment
okay you already mentioned before that
IO is a problem in case of transactional
memory because you can't undo IO so so
how is that in both cases well maybe
I'll just remind the listener is that
you know IO and garbage question is also
difficult this is why we serialize
objects rather than actually writing out
the pointers to disk because if you
write out a pointer to disk and the
garbage collector doesn't know you've
done that you might think the object is
no longer reachable collect the object
and then if you read the address back in
you might think that you can still
access the object and this is why
languages like Java don't let you
actually write addresses out to disk
this is also a challenge in distributed
computing in distributed garbage
collection is a well studied topic that
again is is much more difficult than
than in the non distributed setting and
so here in the analogy I guess the
biggest thing is the first question I'm
people are often asked about
transactional memory is what about i/o
it'll never work with i/o and and I am
optimistic that just like we've learned
how to sort of restrict programs enough
the garbage collection works even in the
presence of i/o hopefully we can do the
same thing for transactional memory yep
false sharing progress guarantees and
static analysis improvements how do they
fit together the performance of both
garbage collection and transactional
memory is not completely under
programmer control you can get a long
way if you really know how garbage
collectors work and you program in
certain ways you can really program
against the garbage collector to get
certain performance benefits
but there are situations where you just
cannot if your memory allocator which is
in sometimes part of your garbage
collector chooses to put two objects on
the same cache line can really hurt your
performance and this is not something
under programmer control mm-hmm it hurts
you both in the memory management
standpoint things might live longer than
you expect and longer in and and hurt
you in the transactional memory
standpoint
sometimes there's false conflicts
there's transactions abort even though
you didn't access the same memory maybe
you're accessing different fields of the
same object but the particular
transaction memory system only detected
things at the at the object level and so
there's an open question the
transactions community of how much we
need to expose this to programmers mm-hm
so that's an example of how things are
not under your control static analysis
optimizations you know certainly
programmers can't control exactly what
compiler optimizations are used and that
can really affect how long Emery lives
and can affect how often transactions
abort and things like that
hmm we recently had an episode well by
the time we published this one it's not
recently anymore about static analysis
tools and there of course they have the
challenge of trying to understand what
the program that program does because a
lot of the semantics is hidden in
complex protocols especially in
concurrent systems so making things more
declarative which is what transactional
memory does of course make static
analysis and therefore error detection
as well as improve performance
enhancements or performance
optimizations makes it much more
feasible right so well the essence of
concurrency as you say in your paper is
basically trading efficiency for
engineering effectiveness right so you
want to make life easier for developers
by providing transactional memory but
they might have well the program might
not be as good or as fast as if it was a
nicely handcrafted and correct block
based system so how much more easy is
going to concurrency going to be once we
have transactional memory what are the
advantages for developers so let me
answer that question once again this is
certainly my perspective but I should be
fair to the community and say some
people point out the transactional
memory can actually be faster the
there's optimistic concurrency yeah and
and that programmers are not
particularly good at handcrafted
lock-based solutions that that are
particularly efficient yes but that was
I was trying to hint at by saying a well
handcrafted and correct and it's and
people probably typically don't do this
it's not clear that lock-based programs
even carefully crafted ones will be
transactional moment transaction when we
may win but I agree with you that even
if transactional memory gives back some
of the straight line performance I have
the ability to write robust parallel
software in an easier way is worth it
yes and I think the biggest reason if I
can pick just one is that it's easier to
you don't have to maintain a locking
protocol you don't have to keep track of
what lock am I going to acquire before I
access this field yep sometimes that's
that is is done for you automatically
and in particular for avoiding deadlock
it's very hard to write an application
if you ever need to hold more than one
lock at once yeah for example if you
need to transfer some data from one
object to another and you need to
acquire both locks well if some other
thread requires the same two locks in
the reverse order you can deadlock and
it's very hard to choose an order hmm so
well just just as a remark the idea of
trading if efficiency for developer
effectiveness is for in transactional
memories of course the same thing for
garbage collection you make things
easier for developers but it might not
be as optimized as if memory was managed
by hand correctly so there is not an
energy exactly absolutely and the
analogy goes further as well that there
are situations where using garbage
collection will be faster than not using
garbage collection now understand the
reason is that when you collect data and
you move objects around you can get them
to fit in cache you can get them to fit
on the same cache line and things like
that you increase locality mm-hm
exactly so will programming of well
concurrent programming be as easy as
sequential process sequential
programming with friends
so memory so this is the key question
that I bring always just because this
analogy is there doesn't mean that we'll
introduce transactional memory and
suddenly parallel programming will be as
easy as sequential programming with
garbage collection not at all
everything about transactional memory is
about from a from a program or
reliability standpoint maybe I shouldn't
say all everything but a big part of it
is letting you just write atomic left
curly brace statement right curly brace
yeah instead of having to choose a
particular lock and worrying about race
conditions and deadlock well what it
doesn't talk about is where should you
put that atomic statement right still
the programmers job to decide what is a
transaction what collection of
operations need to happen all at once
yeah and there's still the trade-off if
you make them too big you'll hurt
performance and you make them too small
you'll hurt correctness yeah and the
analogy doesn't help with that mm-hmm
and it's exactly what does not come up
in sequential programming in sequential
programming there's no idea of what
group of events need to happen all at
once
before another thread sees them because
you're the only thread yeah sure so at
some point you you know sequential
programming is a special case of
parallel programming and in the and and
and so there's not gonna be an analogy
that gets rid it's gonna reduce the
general case to the special case yeah it
just doesn't exist yeah okay so here is
the 1 million dollar question
what's the point of the analogy why did
you write the paper why did I write the
paper for a couple of reasons
one is that I think it's it will really
help with research ok that once you have
an analogy it can motivate new ideas
right you you know I look on the garbage
collection side and I see generational
garbage collection an idea from the
early to mid 80s that has been extremely
important in efficient garbage
collection implementation techniques and
I don't yet see something on the
transactional memory side and if writing
this paper can inspire someone to come
up with something just as important on
transactional memory by thinking what is
you know what is the thing on the other
side I think that would be a huge
advance and so this idea of using an
analogy even an informal one to come up
with new ideas is something I think
humans do all the time
and and I wanted to share this one so
that other people could come up with
ideas less important reasons are I think
it can help explain transactional memory
as you know just to understand what it
is it's a new thing a lot of people know
about garbage collection maybe this will
help them understand some of the
limitations and benefits of
transactional memory it works for me and
the final reason I have to admit is once
I saw these connections I just thought
this was you know one of the most
beautiful things I've ever seen in
computer science and I wanted to share
it yeah absolutely and again I recommend
readers listeners to become readers and
read the paper from the analogy you also
risked a couple of possible predictions
about hardware support and other stuff
right right so I have a section in the
pages you know we've talked really about
the technical stuff you know coding and
software engineering and really the
theory of garbage quotient transactional
memory but then I said you know there's
some other things we can say about
garbage question that might or might not
be true about transactional memory one
is you know a lot of time if you go back
a couple decades or three or four
decades people felt that garbage
question was very slow and absolutely
needed hardware support the old lisp
machine add hardware support for garbage
collection and people don't feel that
way anymore
and so perhaps if we push the analogy a
little too far people will someday feel
the transactional memory doesn't need
hardware support either I just kind of
throw that out almost to be provocative
and the second one is that you know we
had the basic garbage collection
algorithms figured out in the 1960s and
I say we in the general sense I wasn't
even born yet and yet you know garbage
collection in the mainstream we're
really talking the 1990s and so
unfortunately may need to be prepared
for transactional memory to take a
slower road to mainstream adoption and
many of us would like mm-hmm sad message
but probably realistic but you know I'm
actually even though I say that in the
paper and I'm actually optimistic you
know there's all the new high
performance computing languages chapel
from cray x10 from IBM and fortress from
Sun all three of them have an idea of
transactions and the atomic statements
in their draft languages and so you know
should those languages take on and I
take off and I think they're all very
interesting
I think transactions will get out pretty
quickly mm-hmm yeah so playing devil's
advocate and now not with regards to
your analogy but rather to a
transactional memory in general isn't it
a trivial finding that making something
that developers had to implement as
procedural statements protocols making
that part of the language in making that
more declarative isn't it trivial to to
find out that this is an advantage yeah
on that level absolutely moving things
higher level providing runtime services
all of those things in that sense it's
not you know the analogy is so basic so
simple it's just that one idea we could
throw a lot of things in exceptions
getting rid of go to you know a library
support for serialization and process
migration all of these things just just
give something to programmers that they
used to have to do and a tedious and
error-prone way yeah and I think what
goes further here is the idea that
memory management is about reusing
memory as much as you can but not more
and concurrency is about getting as much
to happen in parallel as you can but not
more and that this in some sense it's
it's time versus space memory mansion is
about space parallelism is about time
and garbage collection transactional
memory as solutions are a rather similar
runtime services much more similar than
then I think has been been appreciated
before and I'm you know could you take a
third thing like one of the things I
mentioned like exceptions and try to
write you know four or five
ages of sentence analogy with garbage
collection maybe and if so I'd love to
read it
yeah but I don't think so yeah so that
the remaining challenge you mentioned is
of course the transaction demarcation to
big to small and so on how much can we
learn from the database community how
much interaction is there between the
transactional memory community in the
database folks well there's an old joke
in programming languages that what we do
is we take database solutions from 20
years ago and finally figure out what
they were talking about and there's some
truth to that I feel that myself and
perhaps some of my colleagues and
transactions have not learned as much or
learned as quickly from the database
community as we should but there are
some important differences as well you
know in the database world the data is
is much more structured and the
programming languages if you will things
like SQL and things like that are much
more restrictive on purpose and that
makes sense in that domain in our
general-purpose programming languages
perhaps we should not let you start and
end transactions wherever you want or we
should provide some sort of tools
support for helping you to determine
what invariants are maintained depending
where you start and your transactions
you know maybe they're things are things
to learn from the database community
about where transactions should begin
and end but I do think it's a harder
problem for us I think in the database
world and maybe I'm missing something
you know it's usually easy to say well
you know this update to the personnel
records you know just needs to be a
transaction or this money transfer it
needs to be a transaction and in our
more general-purpose unstructured
applications I'm not sure we programmers
are as good at drawing those lines mm-hm
okay to wrap this up concurrency is
obviously becoming more and more
important and atomic and well
transactional memory is a hot topic
there what other approaches are there on
the horizon that might make concurrency
more tractable for for Joe developer as
as
say for example one thing we talked
about was the message passing stuff in
Erlang or for example also Scala sector
framework or something so what do you
see
so we'll transactional memory is that
the only kid on the block to make things
easier or other alternatives also in the
shared memory space well I think it's
certainly the biggest kid on the block
if you look at research interest and and
that sort of stuff and I think you've
drawn exactly the right distinction that
I think in the space of shared memory
it's in my opinion the biggest and most
intriguing advance we've seen in awhile
now the basic idea is for transactional
memory actually goes back to Elliott
Moss and Mars Herlihy in the mid 80s so
you know a lot of this is is fleshing
out the ideas and and and extending the
idea is being more efficient all the
software stuff came later and so on but
transactional memory is big in the
shared memory space but whenever I talk
about transactions I always say but
that's just in the shared memory space
you know I think there's a huge space
you know Erlang for example not just has
all this message-passing stuff but one
of the reasons it works so well is that
it's a mostly functional language chip
and the great thing about functional
language is it is if you don't mutate
memory your synchronization problems go
away if to a large extent the first
thing when I teach sophomores concurrent
programming which may surprise some of
your listeners that we do now and I
think this will become our comm and
teach sophomores basics of concurrent
programming yeah the first thing I tell
them is don't use concurrent programming
unless you have to yeah second thing I
tell them is don't share data unless you
have to yeah the third thing I tell them
is if you do have to share data don't
mutate it unless you have to
yeah and only when none of that is
appropriate for your application do we
need to start talking about locks and
their hands actions and memory are great
but of course for all these things you
need language support otherwise you you
accidentally modify stuff and then
you're screwed that's right and I think
there's there's a real opportunity here
to revisit a lot of the classic ideas on
programming models language to preface
illusion see message passing
coordination things like that and and
see which of them are going to help us
and I think I'm
always of the opinion that it's not
about finding the best overall solution
and declaring it the winner it's going
to depend on the application and the
language the type of programmers and
it's a really exciting time for
concurrency you know you can be a cynic
and say there's no new ideas or you can
be an optimist and say there's a new
opportunity to extend and adapt those
ideas to to the chicken current
programming because it's so much more
important than it's ever been
yeah ok so that was really really cool
very interesting is there anything I
should have asked you but didn't maybe I
drew just emphasize again this analogy
is really all about perspective and
about taking a big step back and but the
actual research that's making
transactional memory happen has been
done by a lot of really great great
people a lot of colleagues of mine and
and if this analogy can kind of serve to
help popularize or make available some
of their work and that's another
advantage of it you know this was this
was a an insight and an essay that sort
of really mean having the chance to take
a step back and and and it was really
fun to do and fun to talk about with you
and I'll have fun talking about it oops
Allah and but we've got a lot more down
and dirty work to do too and and we're
doing that as well ok then thank you
very much for being on the show you're
welcome
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website
so other people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Cowley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details
[Music]
you